<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://rossettisimone.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://rossettisimone.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-02-11T17:01:37+00:00</updated><id>https://rossettisimone.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal website of Simone Rossetti, AI Research Engineer working on computer vision and vision-language learning. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The State of Digitalisation in EU Agriculture: What the Data Finally Shows</title><link href="https://rossettisimone.github.io/blog/2026/the-state-of-digitalisation-in-eu-agriculture/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The State of Digitalisation in EU Agriculture: What the Data Finally Shows"/><published>2026-01-29T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-29T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rossettisimone.github.io/blog/2026/the-state-of-digitalisation-in-eu-agriculture</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rossettisimone.github.io/blog/2026/the-state-of-digitalisation-in-eu-agriculture/"><![CDATA[<p>How digital is EU agriculture?</p> <p>Until recently, nobody could answer that question with evidence. Digitalisation has been a central pillar of the <strong>Common Agricultural Policy (CAP)</strong> and of the EU Digital Agenda for years, yet there was no EU-wide baseline to measure where farms actually stood.</p> <p>The <strong>Joint Research Centre (JRC)</strong> has now filled that gap. Its report <em>The state of digitalisation in EU agriculture: Insights from farm surveys</em> (JRC141259) is based on <strong>1,444 interviews</strong> with farmers in <strong>nine Member States</strong> (Germany, Ireland, Greece, Spain, France, Italy, Lithuania, Hungary and Poland), conducted between June and October 2024. This is the first systematic snapshot of farm-level digital adoption across the EU.</p> <p>What follows is a narrative reading of the report’s core results, combining key figures, selected charts, and the implications that matter most for policy makers, technology builders, and anyone thinking seriously about AI in agriculture.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="adoption-today-digital-basics-are-widespread-advanced-tools-are-not">Adoption today: digital basics are widespread, advanced tools are not</h2> <p>The first result is unambiguous: <strong>most farms are connected and digitally equipped at a basic level</strong>.</p> <p>Around <strong>85%</strong> of surveyed farms report adequate internet coverage on the farm and in the field, while <strong>15%</strong> still face connectivity constraints. Smartphones and general-purpose digital devices are widespread. The problem is not that farmers are offline.</p> <p>The real divide is between <strong>general IT tools</strong> and <strong>production-specific digital technologies</strong>.</p> <p>About <strong>93%</strong> of farms use at least one general digital tool such as accounting software, weather apps, trading platforms, mobile apps or communication tools, and <strong>68%</strong> use three or more. These tools are familiar, affordable, and perceived as useful.</p> <p>By contrast, adoption of <strong>crop-specific and livestock-specific technologies</strong> remains limited and uneven. For most specialised tools (drones, GNSS tractors, yield mapping, sensors, automatic milking), adoption rates range between <strong>3% and 23%</strong>, depending on the technology. While many farms report using at least one crop-specific (<strong>79%</strong>) or livestock-specific (<strong>83%</strong>) tool, only <strong>29%</strong> use three or more crop technologies and only <strong>17%</strong> three or more livestock technologies.</p> <p>The distribution of total digital adoption is shown below.</p> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-10 d-flex justify-content-center"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-fig-13-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-fig-13-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-fig-13-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-fig-13.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption text-center"> <p><strong>Number of digital technologies adopted by the farmers surveyed (%).</strong> Source: <a href="https://data.europa.eu/doi/10.2760/4688498">JRC</a></p> </div> <p>Adoption increased rapidly between 2008 and 2020, but <strong>has slowed since 2020</strong>. Intentions to adopt new technologies over the next five years are modest. The report links this slowdown to cost pressures and economic uncertainty.</p> <p>The picture that emerges is stable but uneven: the digital foundation is there, yet the layer of advanced, production-focused technologies remains thin.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="what-farmers-adopt-and-what-they-clearly-do-not">What farmers adopt, and what they clearly do not</h2> <p>The report avoids normative labels, but <strong>Figure 15</strong> and Chapter 4.3 make adoption patterns very clear.</p> <p>Farmers adopt technologies they see as <strong>affordable, understandable, and directly useful</strong>. Technologies that fail on these dimensions remain marginal, regardless of how prominent they are in public discourse.</p> <p>Among <strong>crop-specific technologies</strong>, adoption is led by <strong>digital field records</strong>, used by <strong>58%</strong> of respondents. Next come <strong>satellite-based maps</strong> (<strong>22%</strong>) and <strong>farm management software</strong> (<strong>21%</strong>). At the bottom sit <strong>drones</strong>, both for monitoring and spraying, each adopted by <strong>only 3%</strong> of farms. Crucially, <strong>87%</strong> of farmers report no intention to adopt drones in the next five years.</p> <p>Automatic steering, telemetry, yield mapping, field robotics and light-bar guidance cluster between <strong>5% and 9%</strong>. Planned adoption is modest for most tools, typically an additional <strong>9 to 15%</strong> over five years. One notable exception is <strong>georeferenced soil sampling</strong>, which rises from <strong>13%</strong> today to <strong>23%</strong> planned, signalling interest in precision soil data.</p> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-10 d-flex justify-content-center"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-p32-img0-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-p32-img0-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-p32-img0-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-p32-img0.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption text-center"> <p><strong>Adoption rates of crop-specific digital technologies (%).</strong> Source: <a href="https://data.europa.eu/doi/10.2760/4688498">JRC</a>, Chapter 4.3.</p> </div> <p>The livestock side shows the same structure. <strong>Digital livestock records</strong> dominate (<strong>66%</strong>), while cameras, sensors and automation tools lag far behind.</p> <p>The implication is not that drones or robotics lack value. It is that <strong>their value proposition does not scale across farm types at current cost and complexity levels</strong>.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="the-software-layer-is-where-momentum-actually-exists">The software layer is where momentum actually exists</h2> <p>Across both crop and livestock systems, <strong>management software and digital records</strong> sit in a clear adoption sweet spot. These tools are perceived as affordable and useful, and they address a major pain point: <strong>administrative burden</strong>.</p> <p>Data collection and management on farms remain largely manual or semi-digital. Paper records, spreadsheets and scanned documents are common. The report explicitly notes that better digital tools could reduce administrative workload and improve interoperability with advisory services and compliance systems.</p> <p>This aligns tightly with observed adoption. Farmers expand on the <strong>software layer they already trust</strong>, rather than jumping to expensive hardware. From a technology and policy perspective, this is the clearest signal in the report: <strong>platform-centric, software-first solutions match actual demand</strong>.</p> <p>Hardware-heavy technologies, by contrast, face structural friction. Drones, robotics and advanced machinery are expensive, sometimes regulated, and often poorly tailored to diverse farm sizes and production systems. As a result, their adoption remains niche in the medium term.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="what-actually-drives-adoption">What actually drives adoption</h2> <p>When farmers are asked why they adopt digital tools, five drivers dominate: <strong>efficiency gains, cost savings, regulatory pressure, quality of life, and market pressure</strong>.</p> <p>In the report’s econometric analysis, farmers citing these drivers adopt between <strong>8% and 38%</strong> more technologies. Reported barriers include <strong>high costs</strong> and <strong>limited digital skills</strong>, but these barriers are less strongly associated with adoption outcomes than the positive drivers.</p> <p>Public authorities and cooperatives play a relatively small role in triggering adoption. Most uptake is driven by farmers themselves and by close value-chain actors. This suggests room for better-targeted public support.</p> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-10 d-flex justify-content-center"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-fig-27-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-fig-27-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-fig-27-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-fig-27.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption text-center"> <p><strong>Main barriers to digital adoption (%).</strong> Source: <a href="https://data.europa.eu/doi/10.2760/4688498">JRC</a></p> </div> <hr/> <h2 id="data-practices-broad-collection-cautious-sharing">Data practices: broad collection, cautious sharing</h2> <p>Farms collect a wide range of data, from financial records to soil, livestock, and input use. Collection frequency varies, but the real bottleneck is <strong>how data are managed</strong>. Manual and semi-digital processes dominate, reinforcing administrative burden.</p> <p>Electronic data sharing is <strong>selective</strong>. Many farms do not share data at all. Those who do mainly share with <strong>trusted actors</strong> such as advisors, cooperatives and other farmers. Banks, technology firms, researchers and public administrations are much less common recipients.</p> <p>Concerns about <strong>data privacy, security and control</strong> dominate. Farmers share data primarily when they see clear indirect benefits, such as better advice or tailored services.</p> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-10 d-flex justify-content-center"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-fig-31-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-fig-31-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-fig-31-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-fig-31.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption text-center"> <p><strong>Frequency of farm-level data collection (%).</strong> Source: <a href="https://data.europa.eu/doi/10.2760/4688498">JRC</a></p> </div> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-10 d-flex justify-content-center"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-fig-33-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-fig-33-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-fig-33-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-fig-33.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption text-center"> <p><strong>Electronic data sharing with external actors (%).</strong> Source: <a href="https://data.europa.eu/doi/10.2760/4688498">JRC</a></p> </div> <hr/> <h2 id="who-adopts-more-and-why">Who adopts more, and why</h2> <p>Regression analysis confirms familiar patterns. <strong>Larger farms</strong> adopt significantly more technologies, between <strong>10% and 84%</strong> depending on category. Poor connectivity is associated with <strong>4% to 30%</strong> fewer technologies. <strong>Direct sales</strong>, <strong>full-time farming</strong>, and <strong>specialised training</strong> are all positively associated with adoption.</p> <p>Age plays a limited role. Education matters more for general IT than for specialised technologies. Gender, legal form and organic production are largely insignificant.</p> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-10 d-flex justify-content-center"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-page-57-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-page-57-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-page-57-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/jrc141259/jrc-page-57.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption text-center"> <p><strong>Poisson regression results for digital adoption.</strong> Source: <a href="https://data.europa.eu/doi/10.2760/4688498">JRC</a></p> </div> <hr/> <h2 id="what-this-baseline-really-tells-us">What this baseline really tells us</h2> <p>The report does not point to a single policy lever. It points to <strong>heterogeneity</strong>. Adoption differs by technology, farm size, region and production system.</p> <p>The strongest signals are clear:</p> <ul> <li>Connectivity and training matter</li> <li>Administrative burden discourages adoption</li> <li>Software and records deliver visible value</li> <li>Data trust is a prerequisite for AI and advanced analytics</li> </ul> <p>For AI in agriculture, this baseline is especially important. AI adoption will depend on the same factors: cost, perceived benefit, trust, and fit with farm realities. The data suggest a <strong>software-first pathway</strong>, where AI augments management, compliance and decision support before it drives robotics or full automation.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="where-to-explore-the-data">Where to explore the data</h2> <p>This post draws from selected figures in the report. The full dataset can be explored interactively by country, farm size and technology type via the JRC dashboard:</p> <p><strong>JRC DataM: Digitalisation in EU Agriculture</strong><br/> <a href="https://datam.jrc.ec.europa.eu/datam/mashup/DIGITALISATION_IN_EU_AGRICULTURE/">https://datam.jrc.ec.europa.eu/datam/mashup/DIGITALISATION_IN_EU_AGRICULTURE/</a></p> <p><strong>Reference</strong><br/> Tur Cardona, J. et al. <em>The state of digitalisation in EU agriculture: Insights from farm surveys</em>. Publications Office of the European Union, 2025.<br/> DOI: <a href="https://data.europa.eu/doi/10.2760/4688498">https://data.europa.eu/doi/10.2760/4688498</a></p> <p>This is now the empirical baseline for CAP implementation and for the Commission’s work on a digital and AI-ready agri-food sector. The signal is consistent throughout the data: <strong>records and software first; drones and robotics when they demonstrably earn their keep</strong>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><category term="policy"/><category term="agriculture"/><category term="digitalisation"/><category term="EU"/><category term="JRC"/><category term="farm surveys"/><category term="data practices"/><category term="CAP"/><category term="precision agriculture"/><category term="agtech"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Based on 1,444 farm interviews across nine EU countries, the JRC provides the first real baseline of agricultural digitalisation. The message is clear: software and records first, drones and heavy tech later.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Most Insane Machine on Earth: Inside ASML’s EUV Lithography Systems</title><link href="https://rossettisimone.github.io/blog/2026/the-most-insane-machine/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Most Insane Machine on Earth: Inside ASML’s EUV Lithography Systems"/><published>2026-01-22T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-22T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rossettisimone.github.io/blog/2026/the-most-insane-machine</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rossettisimone.github.io/blog/2026/the-most-insane-machine/"><![CDATA[<p>Before we dive into ASML’s EUV machines, it helps to understand how the modern semiconductor ecosystem is structured. Consider a different example: <strong>Apple</strong> designs its <strong>SoCs</strong> (System-on-Chip), <strong>TSMC</strong> (Taiwan Semiconductor Manufacturing Company) manufactures them, and <strong>ASML</strong> provides the <strong>EUV lithography</strong> equipment needed for advanced nodes.</p> <p>The same dynamic holds for <strong>Nvidia</strong> and <strong>AI GPUs</strong>. Nvidia’s Blackwell GPUs require TSMC’s <strong>5 nm</strong> or smaller process technology. TSMC, in turn, relies on ASML’s EUV tools to print the <strong>dense transistor layouts</strong>. A delay or shortage at any point would slow the entire industry.</p> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-10 mt-3 mt-md-0 d-flex justify-content-center"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://www.zdnet.com/a/img/resize/68e026b33e4cae69020f72ba0d5e7564ebdf2c87/2024/03/19/a435deb3-a5e5-4c4f-9d26-964d96a07f18/nvidia-2024-huang-and-blackwell-versus-hopper.png?auto=webp&amp;width=1280" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="https://www.zdnet.com/a/img/resize/68e026b33e4cae69020f72ba0d5e7564ebdf2c87/2024/03/19/a435deb3-a5e5-4c4f-9d26-964d96a07f18/nvidia-2024-huang-and-blackwell-versus-hopper.png?auto=webp&amp;width=1280" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption text-center"> <p><strong>Nvidia co-founder and CEO Jensen Huang compares the new Blackwell GPU to its predecessor, H100 "Hopper," at GTC 2024.</strong></p> </div> <h2 id="what-exactly-is-an-asml-euv-machine">What Exactly Is an ASML EUV Machine?</h2> <p>In the world of semiconductor manufacturing, <em>nothing else even comes close</em> to the engineering scale and complexity of ASML’s extreme ultraviolet (EUV) lithography machines. These behemoths are <strong>the core tools that print the world’s most advanced computer chips</strong>: from the processors in your smartphone to the AI accelerators that train large language models.</p> <swiper-container keyboard="true" navigation="true" pagination="true" pagination-clickable="true" pagination-dynamic-bullets="true" rewind="true"> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://wiot-group.com/storage/1662/ASML-page1-intro-480.webp 480w,https://wiot-group.com/storage/1662/ASML-page1-intro-800.webp 800w,https://wiot-group.com/storage/1662/ASML-page1-intro-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="https://wiot-group.com/storage/1662/ASML-page1-intro.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://newsroom.intel.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/newsroom-intel-high-na-euv-3-scaled-480.webp 480w,https://newsroom.intel.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/newsroom-intel-high-na-euv-3-scaled-800.webp 800w,https://newsroom.intel.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/newsroom-intel-high-na-euv-3-scaled-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="https://newsroom.intel.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/newsroom-intel-high-na-euv-3-scaled.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> <swiper-slide> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://www.imec-int.com/sites/default/files/2021-12/ASML_NXE400_system_print3674_1_0-480.webp 480w,https://www.imec-int.com/sites/default/files/2021-12/ASML_NXE400_system_print3674_1_0-800.webp 800w,https://www.imec-int.com/sites/default/files/2021-12/ASML_NXE400_system_print3674_1_0-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="https://www.imec-int.com/sites/default/files/2021-12/ASML_NXE400_system_print3674_1_0.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </swiper-slide> </swiper-container> <p>At its core, an EUV lithography system is <em>the machine that “prints” circuit patterns on silicon wafers</em> using <strong>extreme ultraviolet light</strong> (EUV, ~13.5 nm wavelength). This short wavelength lets manufacturers create features that are <em>only a few nanometers wide</em>, essential for modern chips below ~7 nm node. (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extreme_ultraviolet_lithography" title="Extreme ultraviolet lithography">Wikipedia</a>)</p> <p>Instead of traditional lenses, these tools use <strong>ultra‑precise mirrors</strong> to project patterns: each must be polished so perfectly that even if scaled up to the size of a country, the largest imperfection would be smaller than a millimeter. (<a href="https://www.asml.com/technology/lithography-principles/lenses-and-mirrors" title="Lenses &amp; mirrors - Lithography principles | ASML">ASML</a>)</p> <p>This precision is not optional, it’s the only way to achieve the accuracy needed to fabricate <strong>billions of transistors in areas smaller than a dust mite.</strong></p> <p>EUV lithography requires a unique combination of extreme ultraviolet light generation, atomic-scale mirrors, vacuum operation, and nanometer-precision mechanics that <strong>only</strong> ASML has successfully developed, integrated, and industrialized at scale.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="the-insane-scale-physically-and-economically">The Insane Scale: Physically and Economically</h2> <h3 id="size--logistics">Size &amp; Logistics</h3> <ul> <li><strong>Weight:</strong> ~180+ metric tons (as heavy as a couple of full‑size cars stacked). (<a href="https://medium.com/%40ASMLcompany/a-backgrounder-on-extreme-ultraviolet-euv-lithography-a5fccb8e99f4" title="A backgrounder on Extreme Ultraviolet (EUV) lithography | by ASML | Medium">Medium</a>)</li> <li><strong>Dimensions:</strong> Roughly the size of a bus, often ~10 m long and several meters high and wide. (<a href="https://help.gadgetmates.com/how-much-do-euv-machines-cost" title="EUV Machines: What They Are, Costs, Lithography Technology - GadgetMates Help">Gadget Help</a>)</li> <li><strong>Transport:</strong> Machines ship in <em>dozens of freight containers</em> and can require <strong>multiple cargo planes, trucks, and months of on‑site assembly</strong> at customer fabs. (<a href="https://medium.com/%40ASMLcompany/a-backgrounder-on-extreme-ultraviolet-euv-lithography-a5fccb8e99f4" title="A backgrounder on Extreme Ultraviolet (EUV) lithography | by ASML | Medium">Medium</a>)</li> <li><strong>Components:</strong> ~100,000 parts, &gt;3,000 cables, ~40,000 bolts, and ~2 km of hosing. (<a href="https://medium.com/%40ASMLcompany/a-backgrounder-on-extreme-ultraviolet-euv-lithography-a5fccb8e99f4" title="A backgrounder on Extreme Ultraviolet (EUV) lithography | by ASML | Medium">Medium</a>)</li> </ul> <h3 id="cost-its-not-a-typo">Cost: It’s Not a Typo</h3> <p>These are among the <strong>most expensive machines ever created</strong>:</p> <table> <thead> <tr> <th>System Type</th> <th style="text-align: right">Typical Cost (USD)</th> <th>Purpose</th> </tr> </thead> <tbody> <tr> <td><strong>EUV</strong> (standard)</td> <td style="text-align: right">~$180M-$250M</td> <td>Advanced chips ~7nm-3nm nodes. (<a href="https://fourweekmba.com/asml-machine-pricing-from-5m-duv-to-724m-hyper-na-euv/" title="ASML Machine Pricing: From $5M DUV to $724M Hyper NA EUV - FourWeekMBA">FourWeekMBA</a>)</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>High‑NA EUV</strong></td> <td style="text-align: right">~$350M-$400M</td> <td>Next‑gen resolution toward ~2nm/1.4nm. (<a href="https://fourweekmba.com/asml-machine-pricing-from-5m-duv-to-724m-hyper-na-euv/" title="ASML Machine Pricing: From $5M DUV to $724M Hyper NA EUV - FourWeekMBA">FourWeekMBA</a>)</td> </tr> <tr> <td><strong>DUV systems</strong></td> <td style="text-align: right">~$5M-$90M</td> <td>Older litho used for mature nodes (auto, IoT). (<a href="https://fourweekmba.com/asml-machine-pricing-from-5m-duv-to-724m-hyper-na-euv/" title="ASML Machine Pricing: From $5M DUV to $724M Hyper NA EUV - FourWeekMBA">FourWeekMBA</a>)</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>Yes, prices routinely <strong>dwarf the cost of passenger aircraft</strong> and rival advanced scientific infrastructure. (<a href="https://www.whatjobs.com/news/the-euv-machine-the-400-million-device-that-built-the-ai-revolution/" title="The EUV Machine: The $400 Million Device That Built the AI Revolution | WhatJobs News">www.whatjobs.com</a>)</p> <hr/> <h2 id="how-it-actually-works-without-exaggeration">How It Actually Works (Without Exaggeration)</h2> <p>Many online videos dramatize the process, but here’s the <strong>real engineering summary</strong>:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Tin droplet generation:</strong> Microscopic droplets of molten tin are fired into a vacuum. (<a href="https://artificialintelligencenews.in/what-is-euv-lithography-and-why-only-asml-can-do-it/" title="What Is EUV Lithography And Why Only ASML Can Do It - Artificial Intelligence News">artificialintelligencenews.in</a>)</li> <li><strong>Laser conversion:</strong> High‑power CO₂ lasers hit the droplets, creating a <strong>plasma hotter than the Sun’s surface</strong> that emits EUV light. (<a href="https://artificialintelligencenews.in/what-is-euv-lithography-and-why-only-asml-can-do-it/" title="What Is EUV Lithography And Why Only ASML Can Do It - Artificial Intelligence News">artificialintelligencenews.in</a>)</li> <li><strong>Optics system:</strong> EUV light reflects off precision mirrors and is <em>projected</em> through a mask that has the chip’s pattern. (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extreme_ultraviolet_lithography" title="Extreme ultraviolet lithography">Wikipedia</a>)</li> <li><strong>Wafer exposure:</strong> The pattern transfers onto a light‑sensitive photoresist on the silicon wafer. (<a href="https://gadgetmates.com/euv-machines-what-they-are-costs-lithography-technology" title="EUV Machines: What They Are, Costs, and Lithography Technology - GadgetMates">GadgetMates</a>)</li> <li><strong>Layer by layer:</strong> This happens <strong>hundreds to thousands of times per wafer</strong>, stacking complex circuits. (<a href="https://gadgetmates.com/euv-machines-what-they-are-costs-lithography-technology" title="EUV Machines: What They Are, Costs, and Lithography Technology - GadgetMates">GadgetMates</a>)</li> </ol> <blockquote> <p><em>From an engineering perspective, EUV lithography is one of the most complex light‑based manufacturing processes ever devised.</em> It requires vacuum optics, nanometer‑precision stages, and lasers synchronized at tens of thousands of pulses per second. (<a href="https://artificialintelligencenews.in/what-is-euv-lithography-and-why-only-asml-can-do-it/" title="What Is EUV Lithography And Why Only ASML Can Do It - Artificial Intelligence News">artificialintelligencenews.in</a>)</p> </blockquote> <div class="row mt-3 justify-content-center"> <div class="col-sm-10 mt-3 mt-md-0 d-flex justify-content-center"> <figure> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/h_zgURwr6nA" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption text-center"> <p><strong>This is how the world’s most advanced chips are made.</strong><br/> ASML’s High-NA EUV TWINSCAN EXE uses extreme ultraviolet light, ultra-precise optics, and massive engineering to print features at <strong>8&nbsp;nm resolution</strong>, boosting imaging contrast by ~40% over previous EUV systems. Bigger machine, smaller transistors and the foundation for the next generation of CPUs, GPUs, and AI chips.</p> </div> <hr/> <h2 id="what-this-means-for-technology">What This Means for Technology</h2> <p>These machines aren’t just expensive curiosities, they are the <strong>foundations of modern computing</strong>:</p> <ul> <li>Every advanced chip in your <strong>smartphones, laptops, AI accelerators, and supercomputers</strong> relies on patterns printed by EUV lithography. (<a href="https://www.whatjobs.com/news/the-euv-machine-the-400-million-device-that-built-the-ai-revolution/" title="The EUV Machine: The $400 Million Device That Built the AI Revolution | WhatJobs News">www.whatjobs.com</a>)</li> <li>Major fabs (TSMC, Samsung, Intel) buy <strong>only ASML’s EUV tools</strong> because no one else offers the same resolution or throughput. (<a href="https://golden.com/wiki/Extreme_ultraviolet_lithography-9A3K9M" title="Extreme ultraviolet lithography | Golden">golden.com</a>)</li> <li>High‑NA machines are now entering production, pushing the industry toward sub‑2 nm nodes. (<a href="https://fourweekmba.com/asml-machine-pricing-from-5m-duv-to-724m-hyper-na-euv/" title="ASML Machine Pricing: From $5M DUV to $724M Hyper NA EUV - FourWeekMBA">FourWeekMBA</a>)</li> </ul> <p>This has <em>global strategic value</em>: access to these machines literally determines which countries and companies can build the most advanced semiconductors. (<a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2025/feb/28/inside-the-mind-bending-tin-blasting-and-hyper-political-world-of-microchips" title="A journey through the hyper-political world of microchips">The Guardian</a>)</p> <hr/> <h2 id="why-it-took-decades-and-billions">Why It Took Decades and Billions</h2> <p>Developing EUV lithography wasn’t just a company project, it was <strong>more than 30 years of R&amp;D across hundreds of suppliers world‑wide</strong>. ASML integrates optics from ZEISS, lasers from specialized vendors, vibration isolation systems, and clean‑room assembly that borders on laboratory‑precision machining. (<a href="https://www.asml.com/technology/lithography-principles/lenses-and-mirrors" title="Lenses &amp; mirrors - Lithography principles | ASML">ASML</a>)</p> <p>The result is a <strong>supply chain and engineering ecosystem so specialized</strong> that replicating it would take enormous time and capital.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="bottom-line-the-most-crucial-machine-youve-never-seen">Bottom Line: The Most Crucial Machine You’ve Never Seen</h2> <p>ASML’s EUV lithography systems are not sci‑fi tech, they are <em>industrial reality</em>:</p> <ul> <li><strong>They enable the chips powering AI, phones, and cloud computing.</strong> (<a href="https://www.whatjobs.com/news/the-euv-machine-the-400-million-device-that-built-the-ai-revolution/" title="The EUV Machine: The $400 Million Device That Built the AI Revolution | WhatJobs News">www.whatjobs.com</a>)</li> <li><strong>They cost hundreds of millions and take months to install.</strong> (<a href="https://fourweekmba.com/asml-machine-pricing-from-5m-duv-to-724m-hyper-na-euv/" title="ASML Machine Pricing: From $5M DUV to $724M Hyper NA EUV - FourWeekMBA">FourWeekMBA</a>)</li> <li><strong>They represent decades of global engineering collaboration.</strong> (<a href="https://www.asml.com/technology/lithography-principles/lenses-and-mirrors" title="Lenses &amp; mirrors - Lithography principles | ASML">ASML</a>)</li> </ul> <p>Next time you think about a smartphone or neural net, remember: <em>the invisible giant behind the scenes is this room‑sized lithography machine, built with the highest engineering precision humanity has ever managed.</em></p> <hr/> <h2 id="references--further-reading">References &amp; Further Reading</h2> <p>🔗 ASML technology overview: <em>optics, numerical aperture, and lithography principles</em> (ASML) <a href="https://www.asml.com/technology/lithography-principles/lenses-and-mirrors">Lenses &amp; Mirrors in EUV Lithography</a></p> <p>🔗 Pricing breakdown: <em>DUV vs. EUV vs. High‑NA</em> <a href="https://fourweekmba.com/asml-machine-pricing-from-5m-duv-to-724m-hyper-na-euv/">ASML Machine Pricing Explained</a></p> <p>🔗 EUV basics: <em>how extreme ultraviolet lithography works</em> <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extreme_ultraviolet_lithography">Extreme Ultraviolet Lithography Explained</a></p> <p>🔗 Industry impact: <em>ASML’s machines and global chipmaking</em> <a href="https://www.whatjobs.com/news/the-euv-machine-the-400-million-device-that-built-the-ai-revolution/">The EUV Machine That Built the AI Revolution</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><category term="industry"/><category term="technology"/><category term="semiconductors"/><category term="euv"/><category term="lithography"/><category term="asml"/><category term="chip-manufacturing"/><category term="hardware"/><category term="nanotechnology"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A deep dive into ASML’s extreme ultraviolet lithography machines: the most complex, expensive, and strategically critical tools in modern semiconductor manufacturing.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How a Token-First Language Axis Is Reshaping Multimodal AI</title><link href="https://rossettisimone.github.io/blog/2026/how-a-token-first-language/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How a Token-First Language Axis Is Reshaping Multimodal AI"/><published>2026-01-21T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-21T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rossettisimone.github.io/blog/2026/how-a-token-first-language</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rossettisimone.github.io/blog/2026/how-a-token-first-language/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="why-we-need-foundational-multimodal-models">Why We Need Foundational Multimodal Models</h2> <p>Today’s AI landscape is fractured. Vision models, language models, and geometric/semantic prediction pipelines each solve narrow tasks. Yet real-world systems—from robotics to complex retrieval agents—require <strong>joint reasoning across perception, structure, and semantics</strong>.</p> <p>Current multimodal systems rely on:</p> <ul> <li>task-specific heads,</li> <li>bespoke pipelines,</li> <li>engineering-heavy loss balancing.</li> </ul> <p>This approach <em>does not scale</em>. It fragments learning into silos instead of enabling true <strong>compositional understanding and control</strong>.</p> <p>We need what language models gave us for text: a <strong>foundation model</strong> whose representations can be queried, composed, and extended without redesigning the architecture for every new task or modality.</p> <p>This is exactly the paradigm shift that <a href="https://4m.epfl.ch/"><em>4M: Massively Multimodal Masked Modeling</em></a> and its scaled variant <a href="https://4m.epfl.ch/"><em>4M-21: An Any-to-Any Vision Model for Tens of Tasks and Modalities</em></a> introduce.</p> <blockquote> <p>“A framework for training any-to-any multimodal foundation models. Scalable. Open-sourced. Across tens of modalities and tasks.” — <a href="https://4m.epfl.ch/"><em>4M official page</em></a></p> </blockquote> <h2 id="unifying-modalities-through-discrete-tokens">Unifying Modalities Through Discrete Tokens</h2> <p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/four_m_site/images/4M_modalities.svg" alt="Modalities overview"/><br/> <em>4M trains a single model to predict any modality from any subset of others using discrete tokenization.</em> (<a href="https://4m.epfl.ch/">Source: 4M project page</a>)</p> <p>At the core of 4M and 4M-21 is <strong>discrete tokenization</strong>:</p> <ul> <li>Images, depth maps, geometry, semantic maps, captions, and feature maps all become sequences of discrete tokens.</li> <li>A <strong>single transformer encoder-decoder</strong> predicts masked tokens from visible ones.</li> <li>There are no task-specific heads or bespoke objectives.</li> </ul> <p>The official site summarizes this succinctly:</p> <blockquote> <p>“By tokenizing modalities into sequences of discrete tokens, we can train a single unified Transformer encoder-decoder on a diverse set of modalities.” (<a href="https://4m.epfl.ch/">Source: 4M project page</a>)</p> </blockquote> <p>This token-centric representation is the <strong>unifying abstraction</strong> that lets one model handle diverse data types without architectural surgery.</p> <h2 id="any-to-any-generation-tasks-become-queries">Any-to-Any Generation: Tasks Become Queries</h2> <p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/four_m_site/videos/4M_chained_generation.mp4#t=32.5" alt="4M chained generation animation"/><br/> <em>4M can generate any modality from any conditioning set in a self-consistent chained manner.</em> (<a href="https://4m.epfl.ch/">Source: 4M project page</a>)</p> <p>One of the most striking capabilities shown on the official page is <strong>any-to-any generation</strong>. Instead of solving fixed tasks like “caption this image” or “predict depth from color”, 4M generates all modalities from whichever subset you choose.</p> <p>The generation works by:</p> <ol> <li>Predicting missing tokens for one modality.</li> <li>Feeding fully generated modalities back into the model.</li> <li>Repeating until all target modalities are generated.</li> </ol> <p>This yields <em>self-consistent, multimodal predictions</em> without loss balancing or head selection (see <a href="https://4m.epfl.ch/">4M project page</a>).</p> <h2 id="fine-grained-control--steerability">Fine-Grained Control &amp; Steerability</h2> <p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/four_m_site/images/4M_editing.svg" alt="Multimodal editing examples"/><br/> <em>4M supports multimodal editing and fine-grained control, such as bounding box–guided RGB generation.</em> (<a href="https://4m.epfl.ch/">Source: 4M project page</a>)</p> <p>Because 4M represents all data in token form, it supports:</p> <ul> <li>partial conditioning (e.g., captions + bounding boxes),</li> <li>semantic and geometric guidance,</li> <li>compositional weighting of conditions.</li> </ul> <p>The official visuals demonstrate how changing a <strong>bounding box</strong> input can reorganize the RGB output—semantic edits become natural rather than hacky (<a href="https://4m.epfl.ch/">4M project page</a>).</p> <h2 id="language-co-training--improved-understanding">Language Co-Training &amp; Improved Understanding</h2> <p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/four_m_site/images/4M_text_understanding.svg" alt="Improved text understanding"/><br/> <em>4M-21 models co-trained with text corpora show stronger text understanding than smaller multimodal variants.</em> (<a href="https://4m.epfl.ch/">Source: 4M project page</a>)</p> <p>4M-21 extends 4M by co-training on large text corpora and incorporating <strong>language as a structural modality</strong> rather than a side condition. The official site notes:</p> <blockquote> <p>“4M models trained on a larger variety of modalities and co-trained on a text corpus exhibit a higher degree of text understanding.” (<a href="https://4m.epfl.ch/">Source: 4M project page</a>)</p> </blockquote> <p>This positions language not just as a human interface, but as a <strong>semantic scaffold</strong> the model uses internally to organize multimodal representations.</p> <h2 id="beyond-generation-retrieval-and-evaluation">Beyond Generation: Retrieval and Evaluation</h2> <p>The official project page also highlights:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Multimodal retrieval</strong> by predicting global embeddings from any modality (<a href="https://4m.epfl.ch/">4M project page</a>).</li> <li><strong>Out-of-the-box evaluations</strong> showing 4M-21’s performance often matches or surpasses specialist baselines and multimodal competitors like Unified-IO (<a href="https://4m.epfl.ch/">4M project page</a>).</li> </ul> <h2 id="authors-and-official-attribution">Authors and Official Attribution</h2> <p>This work is the result of collaboration between EPFL and Apple researchers:</p> <blockquote> <p><em>David Mizrahi, Roman Bachmann, Oğuzhan Fatih Kar, Teresa Yeo, Mingfei Gao, Afshin Dehghan, Amir Zamir… and colleagues</em> — <em>4M &amp; 4M-21 teams</em>.</p> </blockquote> <p>Both papers are available from the <a href="https://4m.epfl.ch/">official 4M project site</a>:</p> <ul> <li><strong>4M: Massively Multimodal Masked Modeling</strong> (NeurIPS 2023) — Mizrahi et al., 2023</li> <li><strong>4M-21: An Any-to-Any Vision Model for Tens of Tasks and Modalities</strong> (NeurIPS 2024) — Bachmann et al., 2024</li> </ul> <h2 id="conclusion-foundations-built-but-the-frontier-remains">Conclusion: Foundations Built, But the Frontier Remains</h2> <p>4M and 4M‑21 mark a turning point in multimodal AI. They show that:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Unified token spaces work across dozens of modalities</strong></li> <li><strong>Language can serve as a structural interface, not just a conditioning signal</strong></li> <li><strong>Tasks can emerge from conditioning rather than engineered heads</strong></li> <li><strong>Models can scale without performance collapse, even as modalities triple</strong></li> </ul> <p>Yet as impressive as these results are, the frontier of <strong>true multimodal intelligence</strong> is still wide open.</p> <h3 id="what-4m21-does-not-doyet">What 4M‑21 Does Not Do—Yet</h3> <p>The project is not a reasoning-first system. It cannot plan, chain steps explicitly, or act autonomously:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Emergent reasoning is limited</strong>: There’s no explicit chain-of-thought or planning; constraint satisfaction occurs implicitly across tokens.</li> <li><strong>Tokenization bottlenecks exist</strong>: Discretization is lossy, which limits fidelity for complex modalities.</li> <li><strong>Dataset alignment is partial</strong>: Some modalities and datasets are only loosely coordinated, leaving room for inconsistencies in training.</li> </ul> <p>In other words, 4M‑21 is a <strong>foundation backbone</strong>, not an agent or cognitive system. It lays the groundwork, but the “thinking” part—planning, instruction-following, and compositional reasoning—is still to come.</p> <h3 id="the-road-ahead-directions-to-watch">The Road Ahead: Directions to Watch</h3> <p>The official project and research notes point to several promising avenues:</p> <ol> <li> <p><strong>Better tokenization schemes</strong><br/> Adaptive, higher-fidelity tokenizers could reduce reconstruction loss and improve fine-grained multimodal generation.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Explicit reasoning objectives</strong><br/> Integrating constraint-based or reasoning-centered training could turn implicit consistency into explicit reasoning capabilities.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Instruction tuning over token sequences</strong><br/> Just like LLMs benefit from instruction fine-tuning, multimodal backbones could learn to follow structured multimodal instructions across domains.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Integration with agentic architectures</strong><br/> Combining unified token spaces with LLM-style planners, memory modules, or embodied agents could finally unlock reasoning and agency in multimodal systems.</p> </li> </ol> <p>In short, 4M‑21 has built the <strong>scalable, unified foundation</strong>, and the next frontier is layering <strong>reasoning, instruction-following, and agency</strong> on top.</p> <blockquote> <p>The lesson for the field is clear: multimodal AI has crossed the threshold of scalability and unification—but intelligence still has a way to go. The foundation is there; now comes the building.</p> </blockquote> <hr/> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <ul> <li><a href="https://4m.epfl.ch/">4M official project page</a>, <em>Massively Multimodal Masked Modeling</em>, EPFL / Apple Research.</li> <li>Bachmann, R., et al. (2024). <em>4M-21: An Any-to-Any Vision Model for Tens of Tasks and Modalities</em>. Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2024). Available at <a href="https://4m.epfl.ch/">4m.epfl.ch</a>.</li> <li>Mizrahi, D., et al. (2023). <em>4M: Massively Multimodal Masked Modeling</em>. Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems (NeurIPS 2023). Available at <a href="https://4m.epfl.ch/">4m.epfl.ch</a>.</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="research"/><category term="ai"/><category term="ai"/><category term="multimodal"/><category term="foundation-models"/><category term="vision-language"/><category term="deep-learning"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Discrete tokens, any-to-any learning, and why language is becoming the operating system of multimodal AI.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The End of Crucial: How the Memory Industry Is Abandoning the Consumer Market</title><link href="https://rossettisimone.github.io/blog/2026/the-end-of-crucial/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The End of Crucial: How the Memory Industry Is Abandoning the Consumer Market"/><published>2026-01-20T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-20T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rossettisimone.github.io/blog/2026/the-end-of-crucial</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rossettisimone.github.io/blog/2026/the-end-of-crucial/"><![CDATA[<p>For nearly thirty years, <strong>Crucial</strong> represented a rare constant in consumer technology: reliable RAM and SSDs, fair pricing, and minimal theatrics.</p> <p>That era is ending.</p> <p>On <strong>3 December 2025</strong>, <strong>Micron Technology Inc. (Nasdaq: MU) announced its decision to exit the consumer memory and storage market</strong>, discontinuing <strong>Crucial-branded products by February 2026</strong>.</p> <p>Shares of the company fell by <strong>roughly 2–3% in afternoon trading</strong> following the announcement, reflecting short-term market reaction rather than a reassessment of Micron’s long-term fundamentals.</p> <p>This is not the story of a declining brand.<br/> It is the story of an industry that has <strong>decided mass-market hardware is no longer strategic</strong>.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="crucials-role-in-the-pc-ecosystem">Crucial’s role in the PC ecosystem</h2> <p>Founded in 1996 as Micron’s consumer arm, Crucial became a pillar of:</p> <ul> <li>DIY PC building</li> <li>affordable workstation upgrades</li> <li>predictable memory compatibility across platforms</li> </ul> <p>Crucial’s competitive advantage was not peak performance, but <strong>trust</strong>.<br/> For many users, it was the default choice precisely because it removed uncertainty from hardware upgrades.</p> <p>Its disappearance leaves a <strong>structural gap</strong>, not merely a branding void.</p> <p><em>Clarification:</em> while consumer brands assemble and market memory modules, <strong>pricing power and supply control ultimately reside with DRAM and NAND manufacturers</strong>. Crucial’s role was downstream; the strategic decision was upstream.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="microns-decision-explicit-and-strategic">Micron’s decision: explicit and strategic</h2> <p>Micron’s announcement left little room for interpretation.</p> <blockquote> <p>“The AI-driven growth in the data center has led to a surge in demand for memory and storage.<br/> Micron has made the difficult decision to exit the Crucial consumer business in order to improve supply and support for our larger, strategic customers in faster-growing segments.”</p> <p>— <em>Sumit Sadana, EVP and Chief Business Officer, Micron Technology</em></p> </blockquote> <p><strong>Source:</strong><br/> Micron Investor Relations<br/> <a href="https://investors.micron.com/news-releases/news-release-details/micron-announces-exit-crucial-consumer-business/">https://investors.micron.com/news-releases/news-release-details/micron-announces-exit-crucial-consumer-business/</a></p> <p>Crucial shipments will continue through Micron’s <strong>fiscal Q2 2026</strong>, and warranties will be honoured.<br/> However, <strong>no further consumer-focused development is planned</strong>.</p> <p>This represents a <strong>long-term reallocation of capital, production capacity, and R&amp;D</strong>, not a temporary retrenchment.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="this-is-not-an-isolated-case">This is not an isolated case</h2> <p>Micron’s move aligns with a broader industry realignment.</p> <p>According to <strong>Reuters</strong>, major memory manufacturers — including <em>Samsung</em> and <em>SK Hynix</em> — are increasingly prioritising <strong>high-performance memory for AI and data centres</strong>, where margins are structurally higher and contracts are longer-term.</p> <p><strong>Source:</strong><br/> Reuters, <em>Micron to exit Crucial consumer memory business</em><br/> <a href="https://www.reuters.com/business/micron-exit-crucial-consumer-memory-business-2025-12-03/">https://www.reuters.com/business/micron-exit-crucial-consumer-memory-business-2025-12-03/</a> The Crucial exit is therefore best understood as a <strong>leading indicator</strong>, not an anomaly.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="memory-pricing-is-rising-but-not-for-the-reasons-consumers-are-told">Memory pricing is rising, but not for the reasons consumers are told</h2> <p>According to <strong>TrendForce</strong> analysis published in December 2025, the sharp increase in memory prices projected for <strong>Q1 2026</strong> is <strong>not driven by a recovery in consumer demand</strong>.</p> <p>Instead, it reflects a <strong>deliberate and structural reallocation of supply</strong> toward <strong>server and AI-centric applications</strong>.</p> <p><strong>Source:</strong><br/> TrendForce via PR Newswire<br/> <a href="https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/memory-makers-prioritize-server-applications-driving-across-the-board-price-increases-in-1q26-says-trendforce-302652560.html">https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/memory-makers-prioritize-server-applications-driving-across-the-board-price-increases-in-1q26-says-trendforce-302652560.html</a></p> <p>TrendForce explicitly states that DRAM suppliers are shifting <strong>advanced process capacity</strong> toward <strong>server DRAM and High Bandwidth Memory (HBM)</strong> to support AI server deployments. This prioritisation tightens availability across all other segments — including those where demand is flat or weakening.</p> <p>The following graphic from TrendForce summarises projected <strong>quarter-on-quarter contract price changes from 4Q25 to 1Q26</strong>:</p> <div style="max-width: 100%; height: auto;"> <img src="https://mma.prnewswire.com/media/2854326/image_800964_36645205.jpg?p=publish" alt="4Q25–1Q26 DRAM &amp; NAND Flash Contract Price Projections" style="width: 100%; height: auto; display: block;"/> </div> <p><em>Source: TrendForce / PR Newswire, January 2026</em></p> <h3 id="what-the-data-shows">What the data shows</h3> <p>Several dynamics are immediately visible:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Conventional DRAM prices</strong> accelerate from roughly <strong>45–50% QoQ in 4Q25</strong> to <strong>55–60% QoQ in 1Q26</strong>, despite weak notebook and PC demand.</li> <li><strong>HBM-blended DRAM</strong>, used in AI accelerators, sustains even stronger pricing momentum.</li> <li><strong>NAND Flash prices</strong> remain elevated at <strong>~33–38% QoQ</strong>, reflecting supply optimisation for enterprise SSDs.</li> </ul> <h3 id="what-this-implies">What this implies</h3> <p>Price increases are occurring <strong>even where market fundamentals would normally suggest moderation</strong>.</p> <p>TrendForce notes that while notebook and consumer electronics demand remains constrained, suppliers are <strong>actively limiting shipments</strong> to these channels. Capacity is instead funnelled toward customers able to commit to <strong>large, long-term, high-margin contracts</strong> — primarily hyperscalers and AI infrastructure operators.</p> <p>To make this divergence explicit, the chart below compares <strong>projected 1Q26 contract price increases by segment</strong>, using only TrendForce-reported values.</p> <pre><code class="language-plotly">{
  "data": [
    {
      "x": ["Server DRAM", "Conventional DRAM", "Client SSD"],
      "y": [60, 57.5, 40],
      "type": "bar",
      "text": [
        "AI servers and CSP capacity pre-booking",
        "Shipment controls despite weak PC demand",
        "NAND output redirected to enterprise SSDs"
      ],
      "hovertemplate": "%{x}&lt;br&gt;%{y}% QoQ increase&lt;br&gt;%{text}&lt;extra&gt;&lt;/extra&gt;"
    }
  ],
  "layout": {
    "title": {
      "text": "Projected 1Q26 Memory Contract Price Increases by Segment (TrendForce)"
    },
    "yaxis": {
      "title": "Quarter-on-Quarter Price Increase (%)",
      "rangemode": "tozero"
    }
  }
}
</code></pre> <p><em>Methodology note:</em> Conventional DRAM uses the midpoint of the reported 55–60% range. No extrapolation beyond published data has been performed.</p> <p><strong>Conclusion:</strong> the consumer memory market is no longer optimised for <strong>stability or affordability</strong>. It is increasingly treated as <strong>residual output</strong> of an industry tuned for AI workloads.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="what-consumers-will-actually-experience">What consumers will actually experience</h2> <p>The exit of Crucial has immediate, practical consequences:</p> <ul> <li>fewer affordable memory options</li> <li>higher baseline prices for upgrades</li> <li>reduced competitive pressure in the mid-range</li> </ul> <p>According to <strong>Tom’s Hardware</strong>, NAND production costs have risen sharply, pushing SSD and RAM prices upward across consumer segments.</p> <p><strong>Source:</strong> Tom’s Hardware, <em>RAM and SSD prices will continue to rise</em> <a href="https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/ram/dont-wait-if-youre-planning-to-upgrade-your-ram-or-ssd-kingston-rep-warns-says-prices-will-continue-to-go-up-nand-costs-up-246-percent">https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/ram/dont-wait-if-youre-planning-to-upgrade-your-ram-or-ssd-kingston-rep-warns-says-prices-will-continue-to-go-up-nand-costs-up-246-percent</a></p> <p>This disproportionately affects:</p> <ul> <li>students</li> <li>freelancers</li> <li>small studios</li> <li>mainstream laptop buyers</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="revenue-follows-ai">Revenue follows AI</h2> <p>Micron’s decision reflects where revenue growth is now concentrated.</p> <p>Based on earnings calls and <strong>Reuters financial analysis</strong>, data centre and AI-related memory now account for a rapidly growing share of revenue, while consumer segments stagnate.</p> <h3 id="micron-revenue-focus-consumer-vs-data-centre-qualitative-shift">Micron revenue focus: consumer vs data centre (qualitative shift)</h3> <pre><code class="language-plotly">{
  "data": [
    {
      "type": "bar",
      "name": "Consumer Memory",
      "x": ["Past (Pre-AI boom)", "Current"],
      "y": [1, 0.5]
    },
    {
      "type": "bar",
      "name": "Data Centre &amp; AI",
      "x": ["Past (Pre-AI boom)", "Current"],
      "y": [0.6, 1.2]
    }
  ],
  "layout": {
    "title": {
      "text": "Relative Revenue Emphasis Shift (Illustrative, Source-Based)"
    },
    "yaxis": {
      "title": "Relative Revenue Weight (Indexed)"
    },
    "barmode": "group"
  }
}
</code></pre> <p><em>Important clarification:</em> this chart is <strong>illustrative</strong>, reflecting directional emphasis described in earnings calls rather than exact revenue percentages.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="counterargument-what-if-ai-demand-slows">Counterargument: what if AI demand slows?</h2> <p>A common counterargument is that AI infrastructure demand may normalise, freeing capacity back to consumer markets.</p> <p>However, this assumes manufacturers are willing to retool <strong>advanced process nodes</strong> for <strong>lower-margin consumer products</strong> — an assumption not supported by current capital allocation trends. Once fabs, contracts, and roadmaps are optimised for hyperscale customers, reversion is economically unattractive.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="the-hidden-risk-of-over-concentration">The hidden risk of over-concentration</h2> <p>The semiconductor industry is historically cyclical.</p> <p>By concentrating production and investment almost entirely on AI and enterprise demand:</p> <ul> <li>flexibility decreases</li> <li>exposure to demand normalisation increases</li> <li>consumer trust erodes</li> </ul> <p>Crucial’s exit is therefore not merely a cost decision, but a <strong>strategic bet on the durability of AI-driven demand</strong>.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="conclusion-crucial-is-a-symptom-not-the-disease">Conclusion: Crucial is a symptom, not the disease</h2> <p>Crucial did not disappear because it failed. It disappeared because it <strong>no longer fit an industry optimised for AI margins</strong>.</p> <p>For consumers, this likely means:</p> <ul> <li>higher prices</li> <li>fewer choices</li> <li>longer upgrade cycles</li> </ul> <p>The memory market is being reshaped in real time. The more relevant question may be whether the consumer memory segment will <strong>ever again be treated as a first-class priority</strong> in a post-AI semiconductor industry.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="sources">Sources</h2> <ul> <li>Micron Investor Relations — <a href="https://investors.micron.com/">https://investors.micron.com/</a></li> <li>Reuters, semiconductor and memory market analysis — <a href="https://www.reuters.com/">https://www.reuters.com/</a></li> <li>TrendForce, memory pricing reports — <a href="https://www.trendforce.com/">https://www.trendforce.com/</a></li> <li>Tom’s Hardware, component pricing commentary — <a href="https://www.tomshardware.com/">https://www.tomshardware.com/</a></li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology"/><category term="industry"/><category term="memory"/><category term="ai"/><category term="semiconductors"/><category term="hardware"/><category term="market"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Micron’s decision to discontinue Crucial marks a structural shift in the memory industry, driven by AI demand and rising prices.]]></summary></entry></feed>