<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://rossettisimone.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://rossettisimone.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-21T15:08:54+00:00</updated><id>https://rossettisimone.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal website of Simone Rossetti — AI Research Engineer working on computer vision and vision-language learning. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The End of Crucial: How the Memory Industry Is Abandoning the Consumer Market</title><link href="https://rossettisimone.github.io/blog/2026/the-end-of-crucial/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The End of Crucial: How the Memory Industry Is Abandoning the Consumer Market"/><published>2026-01-19T11:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-19T11:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rossettisimone.github.io/blog/2026/the-end-of-crucial</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rossettisimone.github.io/blog/2026/the-end-of-crucial/"><![CDATA[<p>For nearly thirty years, <strong>Crucial</strong> represented a rare constant in consumer technology: reliable RAM and SSDs, fair pricing, and minimal theatrics.</p> <p>That era is ending.</p> <p>On <strong>3 December 2025</strong>, <strong>Micron Technology Inc. (Nasdaq: MU) announced its decision to exit the consumer memory and storage market</strong>, discontinuing <strong>Crucial-branded products by February 2026</strong>.</p> <p>Shares of the company fell by <strong>roughly 2–3% in afternoon trading</strong> following the announcement, reflecting short-term market reaction rather than a reassessment of Micron’s long-term fundamentals.</p> <p>This is not the story of a declining brand.<br/> It is the story of an industry that has <strong>decided mass-market hardware is no longer strategic</strong>.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="crucials-role-in-the-pc-ecosystem">Crucial’s role in the PC ecosystem</h2> <p>Founded in 1996 as Micron’s consumer arm, Crucial became a pillar of:</p> <ul> <li>DIY PC building</li> <li>affordable workstation upgrades</li> <li>predictable memory compatibility across platforms</li> </ul> <p>Crucial’s competitive advantage was not peak performance, but <strong>trust</strong>.<br/> For many users, it was the default choice precisely because it removed uncertainty from hardware upgrades.</p> <p>Its disappearance leaves a <strong>structural gap</strong>, not merely a branding void.</p> <p><em>Clarification:</em> while consumer brands assemble and market memory modules, <strong>pricing power and supply control ultimately reside with DRAM and NAND manufacturers</strong>. Crucial’s role was downstream; the strategic decision was upstream.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="microns-decision-explicit-and-strategic">Micron’s decision: explicit and strategic</h2> <p>Micron’s announcement left little room for interpretation.</p> <blockquote> <p>“The AI-driven growth in the data center has led to a surge in demand for memory and storage.<br/> Micron has made the difficult decision to exit the Crucial consumer business in order to improve supply and support for our larger, strategic customers in faster-growing segments.”</p> <p>— <em>Sumit Sadana, EVP and Chief Business Officer, Micron Technology</em></p> </blockquote> <p><strong>Source:</strong><br/> Micron Investor Relations<br/> <a href="https://investors.micron.com/news-releases/news-release-details/micron-announces-exit-crucial-consumer-business/">https://investors.micron.com/news-releases/news-release-details/micron-announces-exit-crucial-consumer-business/</a></p> <p>Crucial shipments will continue through Micron’s <strong>fiscal Q2 2026</strong>, and warranties will be honoured.<br/> However, <strong>no further consumer-focused development is planned</strong>.</p> <p>This represents a <strong>long-term reallocation of capital, production capacity, and R&amp;D</strong>, not a temporary retrenchment.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="this-is-not-an-isolated-case">This is not an isolated case</h2> <p>Micron’s move aligns with a broader industry realignment.</p> <p>According to <strong>Reuters</strong>, major memory manufacturers — including <em>Samsung</em> and <em>SK Hynix</em> — are increasingly prioritising <strong>high-performance memory for AI and data centres</strong>, where margins are structurally higher and contracts are longer-term.</p> <p><strong>Source:</strong><br/> Reuters, <em>Micron to exit Crucial consumer memory business</em><br/> <a href="https://www.reuters.com/business/micron-exit-crucial-consumer-memory-business-2025-12-03/">https://www.reuters.com/business/micron-exit-crucial-consumer-memory-business-2025-12-03/</a> The Crucial exit is therefore best understood as a <strong>leading indicator</strong>, not an anomaly.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="memory-pricing-is-rising-but-not-for-the-reasons-consumers-are-told">Memory pricing is rising, but not for the reasons consumers are told</h2> <p>According to <strong>TrendForce</strong> analysis published in December 2025, the sharp increase in memory prices projected for <strong>Q1 2026</strong> is <strong>not driven by a recovery in consumer demand</strong>.</p> <p>Instead, it reflects a <strong>deliberate and structural reallocation of supply</strong> toward <strong>server and AI-centric applications</strong>.</p> <p><strong>Source:</strong><br/> TrendForce via PR Newswire<br/> <a href="https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/memory-makers-prioritize-server-applications-driving-across-the-board-price-increases-in-1q26-says-trendforce-302652560.html">https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/memory-makers-prioritize-server-applications-driving-across-the-board-price-increases-in-1q26-says-trendforce-302652560.html</a></p> <p>TrendForce explicitly states that DRAM suppliers are shifting <strong>advanced process capacity</strong> toward <strong>server DRAM and High Bandwidth Memory (HBM)</strong> to support AI server deployments. This prioritisation tightens availability across all other segments — including those where demand is flat or weakening.</p> <p>The following graphic from TrendForce summarises projected <strong>quarter-on-quarter contract price changes from 4Q25 to 1Q26</strong>:</p> <div style="max-width: 100%; height: auto;"> <img src="https://mma.prnewswire.com/media/2854326/image_800964_36645205.jpg?p=publish" alt="4Q25–1Q26 DRAM &amp; NAND Flash Contract Price Projections" style="width: 100%; height: auto; display: block;"/> </div> <p><em>Source: TrendForce / PR Newswire, January 2026</em></p> <h3 id="what-the-data-shows">What the data shows</h3> <p>Several dynamics are immediately visible:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Conventional DRAM prices</strong> accelerate from roughly <strong>45–50% QoQ in 4Q25</strong> to <strong>55–60% QoQ in 1Q26</strong>, despite weak notebook and PC demand.</li> <li><strong>HBM-blended DRAM</strong>, used in AI accelerators, sustains even stronger pricing momentum.</li> <li><strong>NAND Flash prices</strong> remain elevated at <strong>~33–38% QoQ</strong>, reflecting supply optimisation for enterprise SSDs.</li> </ul> <h3 id="what-this-implies">What this implies</h3> <p>Price increases are occurring <strong>even where market fundamentals would normally suggest moderation</strong>.</p> <p>TrendForce notes that while notebook and consumer electronics demand remains constrained, suppliers are <strong>actively limiting shipments</strong> to these channels. Capacity is instead funnelled toward customers able to commit to <strong>large, long-term, high-margin contracts</strong> — primarily hyperscalers and AI infrastructure operators.</p> <p>To make this divergence explicit, the chart below compares <strong>projected 1Q26 contract price increases by segment</strong>, using only TrendForce-reported values.</p> <pre><code class="language-plotly">{
  "data": [
    {
      "x": ["Server DRAM", "Conventional DRAM", "Client SSD"],
      "y": [60, 57.5, 40],
      "type": "bar",
      "text": [
        "AI servers and CSP capacity pre-booking",
        "Shipment controls despite weak PC demand",
        "NAND output redirected to enterprise SSDs"
      ],
      "hovertemplate": "%{x}&lt;br&gt;%{y}% QoQ increase&lt;br&gt;%{text}&lt;extra&gt;&lt;/extra&gt;"
    }
  ],
  "layout": {
    "title": {
      "text": "Projected 1Q26 Memory Contract Price Increases by Segment (TrendForce)"
    },
    "yaxis": {
      "title": "Quarter-on-Quarter Price Increase (%)",
      "rangemode": "tozero"
    }
  }
}
</code></pre> <p><em>Methodology note:</em> Conventional DRAM uses the midpoint of the reported 55–60% range. No extrapolation beyond published data has been performed.</p> <p><strong>Conclusion:</strong> the consumer memory market is no longer optimised for <strong>stability or affordability</strong>. It is increasingly treated as <strong>residual output</strong> of an industry tuned for AI workloads.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="what-consumers-will-actually-experience">What consumers will actually experience</h2> <p>The exit of Crucial has immediate, practical consequences:</p> <ul> <li>fewer affordable memory options</li> <li>higher baseline prices for upgrades</li> <li>reduced competitive pressure in the mid-range</li> </ul> <p>According to <strong>Tom’s Hardware</strong>, NAND production costs have risen sharply, pushing SSD and RAM prices upward across consumer segments.</p> <p><strong>Source:</strong> Tom’s Hardware, <em>RAM and SSD prices will continue to rise</em> <a href="https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/ram/dont-wait-if-youre-planning-to-upgrade-your-ram-or-ssd-kingston-rep-warns-says-prices-will-continue-to-go-up-nand-costs-up-246-percent">https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/ram/dont-wait-if-youre-planning-to-upgrade-your-ram-or-ssd-kingston-rep-warns-says-prices-will-continue-to-go-up-nand-costs-up-246-percent</a></p> <p>This disproportionately affects:</p> <ul> <li>students</li> <li>freelancers</li> <li>small studios</li> <li>mainstream laptop buyers</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="revenue-follows-ai">Revenue follows AI</h2> <p>Micron’s decision reflects where revenue growth is now concentrated.</p> <p>Based on earnings calls and <strong>Reuters financial analysis</strong>, data centre and AI-related memory now account for a rapidly growing share of revenue, while consumer segments stagnate.</p> <h3 id="micron-revenue-focus-consumer-vs-data-centre-qualitative-shift">Micron revenue focus: consumer vs data centre (qualitative shift)</h3> <pre><code class="language-plotly">{
  "data": [
    {
      "type": "bar",
      "name": "Consumer Memory",
      "x": ["Past (Pre-AI boom)", "Current"],
      "y": [1, 0.5]
    },
    {
      "type": "bar",
      "name": "Data Centre &amp; AI",
      "x": ["Past (Pre-AI boom)", "Current"],
      "y": [0.6, 1.2]
    }
  ],
  "layout": {
    "title": {
      "text": "Relative Revenue Emphasis Shift (Illustrative, Source-Based)"
    },
    "yaxis": {
      "title": "Relative Revenue Weight (Indexed)"
    },
    "barmode": "group"
  }
}
</code></pre> <p><em>Important clarification:</em> this chart is <strong>illustrative</strong>, reflecting directional emphasis described in earnings calls rather than exact revenue percentages.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="counterargument-what-if-ai-demand-slows">Counterargument: what if AI demand slows?</h2> <p>A common counterargument is that AI infrastructure demand may normalise, freeing capacity back to consumer markets.</p> <p>However, this assumes manufacturers are willing to retool <strong>advanced process nodes</strong> for <strong>lower-margin consumer products</strong> — an assumption not supported by current capital allocation trends. Once fabs, contracts, and roadmaps are optimised for hyperscale customers, reversion is economically unattractive.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="the-hidden-risk-of-over-concentration">The hidden risk of over-concentration</h2> <p>The semiconductor industry is historically cyclical.</p> <p>By concentrating production and investment almost entirely on AI and enterprise demand:</p> <ul> <li>flexibility decreases</li> <li>exposure to demand normalisation increases</li> <li>consumer trust erodes</li> </ul> <p>Crucial’s exit is therefore not merely a cost decision, but a <strong>strategic bet on the durability of AI-driven demand</strong>.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="conclusion-crucial-is-a-symptom-not-the-disease">Conclusion: Crucial is a symptom, not the disease</h2> <p>Crucial did not disappear because it failed. It disappeared because it <strong>no longer fit an industry optimised for AI margins</strong>.</p> <p>For consumers, this likely means:</p> <ul> <li>higher prices</li> <li>fewer choices</li> <li>longer upgrade cycles</li> </ul> <p>The memory market is being reshaped in real time. The more relevant question may be whether the consumer memory segment will <strong>ever again be treated as a first-class priority</strong> in a post-AI semiconductor industry.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="sources">Sources</h2> <ul> <li>Micron Investor Relations — <a href="https://investors.micron.com/">https://investors.micron.com/</a></li> <li>Reuters, semiconductor and memory market analysis — <a href="https://www.reuters.com/">https://www.reuters.com/</a></li> <li>TrendForce, memory pricing reports — <a href="https://www.trendforce.com/">https://www.trendforce.com/</a></li> <li>Tom’s Hardware, component pricing commentary — <a href="https://www.tomshardware.com/">https://www.tomshardware.com/</a></li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology"/><category term="industry"/><category term="memory"/><category term="ai"/><category term="semiconductors"/><category term="hardware"/><category term="market"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Micron’s decision to discontinue Crucial marks a structural shift in the memory industry, driven by AI demand and rising prices.]]></summary></entry></feed>